[
  {
    "q_zh": "請問京都議定書規定幾個工業國家的二氧化碳排放量限制？", 
    "q_en": "How many industrial nations does the Kyoto Protocol restrict the carbon dioxide emission of?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT" 
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問首位自費太空旅行的觀光客為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first self-financed space tourist?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問國家三級古蹟藍田書院位於何地？", 
    "q_en": "Where is Taiwan’s rating-3 historic site \"Lantian Academy\" located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年台灣被指控酒後性侵害酒店小姐的地下樂團為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which underground band was accused of sexually abusing bar attendants under the influence of alcohol in Taiwan in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全台第一個防災公園坐落於台中縣哪個地方？", 
    "q_en": "Where in Taichung County is Taiwan’s first anti-disaster park located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問立法委員羅福助因景文案和哪位立法委員發生劇烈肢體衝突？", 
    "q_en": "Which legislator did Legislator Lo Fu-Chu come into fierce physical conflict with because of the \"Jin-Wen Case?\"", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問香港富商李嘉誠旗下的哪家公司的併購案成為台灣出版產業被外資大規模併購的歷史首例？", 
    "q_en": "Which one of Hong Kong businessman Lee Ka-shin’s company is responsible for the first large-scale foreign merger and acquisition case in Taiwan’s publishing industry?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問東方科學園區位於何地？", 
    "q_en": "Where is the Eastern Science Park?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問誰發明了大易輸入法？", 
    "q_en": "Who invented the Dayi input method?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "新疆北部由天山和阿爾泰山所包夾的盆地是什麼？", 
    "q_en": "Which basin is surrounded by Tianshan Mountain and Altai Mountain of northern Xingjiang?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_MOUNTAIN"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問金氏世界紀錄中最長（1650CM）的髮繡作品是？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of the longest (1650 cm) hair embroidery piece in the Guinness World Record?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ART"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問中國哪個朝代是首見的草原游牧民族統一政權？", 
    "q_en": "Which Chinese dynasty was the first to be governed by grassland nomads?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_RANGE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問西班牙電影「睜開你的雙眼」（Abre Los Ojos）被美國人翻拍成哪部電影？", 
    "q_en": "Which American movie is the remake of the Spanish movie Abre Los Ojos?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問「蜀道之難難於上青天」這句詩出自何詩人之手？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of the poem \"Traveling on the Roads of Shu is Harder than Scaling the Blue Sky?\"", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問大西海子水庫位於哪條河道上？", 
    "q_en": "Which river is the Daxihaizi Reservoir on?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_RIVER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年時，全球最大的濱海風力發電園區在何國啟用？", 
    "q_en": "Which country launched the world’s biggest offshore wind power in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問哪位中國歌唱家是世界三大男高音之一帕華洛帝的首位亞洲入門弟子？", 
    "q_en": "Which Chinese singer is the first Asian student of Pavarotti of The Three Tenors?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全台灣第一個蜜蜂博物館─蜂采館設於何地？", 
    "q_en": "Where is Taiwan’s first bee museum located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "在1971年美國哪艘太空船曾由月球帶回來的岩石切片？", 
    "q_en": "Which American spacecraft brought back rock samples from the moon in 1971?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "VEHICLE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年日本首相小泉純一郎因參拜哪一個神社使得鄰近各國紛紛提出嚴正抗議？", 
    "q_en": "Which shrine caused Japanese Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi to be criticized by neighboring nations for visiting it in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_BUILDING"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "前南聯總統米羅塞維奇受審的聯合國戰犯法庭位於何處？", 
    "q_en": "Where did the UN War Crime Tribunal which tried the former president of Yugoslavia, Milosevic, take place?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問位於台北大稻埕俗稱「鹽館」的辜宅，是1910年哪個辜家人所創建？", 
    "q_en": "Which member of the Koo family built a mansion, which is also known as the \"Salt Hall\", in Tataocheng of Taipei in 1910?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「亞洲廢棄物管理傑出獎」是由歐盟執委會和新加坡政府組成的什麼組織所頒發？", 
    "q_en": "Which organization under the European Commission and Singapore government grants the Asia Waste Management Excellence Award 2001?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_POLITICALSYSTEM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問台灣首支進軍大陸職籃比賽的隊伍是？", 
    "q_en": "Which Taiwanese basketball team was the first to compete in China?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_SPORTTEAM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問台北市那家知名購物中心是由一個球形建築和L形建築所構成？", 
    "q_en": "Which well-known shopping mall in Taipei City is made up of a spherical structure and an L-shaped structure?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_BUILDING"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問在古巴隊在2001年前34屆的世界盃棒球比賽中共拿下幾次冠軍？", 
    "q_en": "How many of the 34 World Cup Baseball championships did the Cuba team win before 2001?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年在美國發現最大的完整蟑螂化石有幾公分長？", 
    "q_en": "What is the length in centimeters of the largest full cockroach fossil that was discovered in the U.S. in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_LENGTH"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問第一位獲得台大名譽博士學位的是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first person to earn an honorary doctoral degree at the National University of Taiwan?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "良渚文化是那條河下游古代文明文化發展的源頭？", 
    "q_en": "Which river’s lower reaches are the originating place of the Liangzhu Culture?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_RIVER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問中國唯一有兩位帝王合葬的陵園且有「唐陵之冠」稱號的是位於西安的？", 
    "q_en": "Where in Xi’an does the only Chinese tomb where two emperors are buried together lie?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_BUILDING"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年哪位大陸藝人因為穿著「日本軍旗裝」走秀，引發大陸民眾一片撻伐？", 
    "q_en": "Which Chinese actor/actress angered the Chinese people because he/she wore a dress with a pattern resembling a Japanese flag in a fashion show?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問獨家報導雜誌曾以哪位政治人物的性愛偷拍光碟搭配其週刊販售？", 
    "q_en": "Which politician did the Scoopweekly sell the secretly-shot sex video of with the weekly magazine?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問台灣童謠「天黑黑」是由哪位作曲家所創作？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the composer of the Taiwanese nursery rhyme \"Dark Dark Sky?\"", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問進行九一一恐怖攻擊行動的回教激進恐怖組織為？", 
    "q_en": "Which Muslim terrorist group is responsible for the 911 attack?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_POLITICALSYSTEM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問巴勒斯坦解放組織的領袖為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the leader of Pakistan Liberation Organization?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問歐洲聯盟決議於何年開始統一使用歐元？", 
    "q_en": "In what year did the European Union choose to be the year for starting to use Euro?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問世界貿易組織於哪一年審議通過中國加入WTO？", 
    "q_en": "In what year did the WTO accept China into membership?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年犯下王室滅門血案的尼泊爾王儲為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Which Nepal crown prince is responsible for the mass murder of the royal family in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年G8會議於何地舉行？", 
    "q_en": "Where did the 2001 G8 Summit take place?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問麥可喬丹二次復出NBA加入何隊？", 
    "q_en": "Which team did Michael Jordan join when he returned to the NBA for the second time?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_SPORTTEAM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問MLB單季73支全壘打紀錄的締造者邦茲效力於何隊？", 
    "q_en": "Which team does Barry Bonds, the recorder setter for hitting 73 homeruns in a single MLB season, belong to?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_SPORTTEAM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000~2001年賽季NBA總冠軍為何隊？", 
    "q_en": "Which team won the NBA championship in the 2000-2001 season?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_SPORTTEAM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國職棒大聯盟運動家吉昂比轉隊至紐約的合約中簽定的年薪是多少？", 
    "q_en": "What is the yearly salary stated in MLB Jason Giambi’s contract with the New York Yankees when Giambi transferred to New York?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國職棒大聯盟首位獲得例行賽MVP的日本籍野手是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Which Japanese fielder is the first to win the MLB MVP?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年奪得澳洲公開賽女單冠軍的網球選手為？", 
    "q_en": "Which tennis player won the 2001 Australian Open Women’s Single game?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年奪得法國公開賽女單冠軍的網球選手為？", 
    "q_en": "Which tennis won the 2001 French Open Women’s Single game?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年遭刺殺身亡的剛果民主共和國總統為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Which Congo president was assassinated in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全球第一個通過醫學用複製胚胎合法化的國家是？", 
    "q_en": "Which country was the first in the world to legalized embryo cloning for medical use?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問印尼史上第一位女總統為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first female Indonesian president?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問涉嫌對台軍售弊案的前法國外長為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Which former French Minister of Foreign Affairs was involved in the Taiwan’s armament purchase scandal?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問一奈米有多長？", 
    "q_en": "How long is one nanometer?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_LENGTH"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問日本政府放任日圓貶值的價位約在？", 
    "q_en": "What value does the Japanese government decide to deflate yen to?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_RATE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國史上最大宗的企業破產事件為哪一家企業？", 
    "q_en": "What is largest company bankruptcy case in the US history?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問微軟的總裁為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is Microsoft’s president?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問首位遭到司法當局起訴逮捕的菲律賓前總統為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Which former Philippine president is the first to be arrested by the judicial bureau?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問由董氏基金會發起向國際菸草商控告求償的賠償金額約為？", 
    "q_en": "What is the amount of indemnity that John Tung Foundation asks international tobacco companies to pay?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問首位公開承認同性戀身分的柏林市市長為？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first Berlin mayor to publicly admit that he is a gay?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年9月1日新宿歌舞伎町大火共造成多少人死亡？", 
    "q_en": "What are the casualties in the Shinjuku Kabuki-cho fire on September 1st, 2001?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問日本為支援美國反恐戰爭所通過的法案為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which law was passed by Japan to support the US anti-terrorism war?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "LAW"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國為發展NMD欲退出哪一項條約？", 
    "q_en": "Which treaty does the US wish to withdraw from in order to develop NMD?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "LAW"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問首家完成人類基因圖譜解碼的公司為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which company is the first to finish sequencing the entire human genome?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年率領自由聯盟於國會選舉獲勝並再度出任總理的義大利前總理為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Which former Italian premier led Casa Liberta to victory in the congress and become the premier once again in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國史上首位非洲裔國務卿為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first African-American Secretary of State in the US?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問涉嫌強暴琉球女子的嘉手納基地駐日美軍空軍技術員為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Which American Air Force personnel in the Kadena Air Force Base is accused of attempted rape of an Okinawa girl?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問哪家航空公司收購全美航空的計畫案因違反托辣斯法被迫取消？", 
    "q_en": "Which airline company’s plan to acquire US Airways was forced to be cancelled because it violated the Hart-Scott-Rodino Antitrust Improvements Act?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年歌劇「阿伊達」的作曲家是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the composer of Opera Aida?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問21世紀第一次月全食是在2001年的幾月幾日？", 
    "q_en": "What is the date of the first lunar eclipse in the 21st century in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_DATE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問希臘籍貨輪阿瑪斯號在臺灣何地外海擱淺沉沒？", 
    "q_en": "The Greek freighter Amorgos sank off the coast of which place in Taiwan?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "UNKNOWN"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問獲得第14屆國際蕭邦鋼琴大賽首獎為哪位華人？", 
    "q_en": "Which Chinese won the 14th International Frederick Chopin Piano Competition?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問在2001年全球生活最昂貴的城市中，台北市排名第幾？", 
    "q_en": "What is the rank of Taipei in the world’s most expensive cities in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_ORDER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問誰是全世界第一位接受手臂移植的人？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first person in the world to receive arm transplant?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全球首見的人類狂牛症「賈庫氏症」在1996年於何國被發現？", 
    "q_en": "Which country held the world’s first discovered case of Creutzfeldt Jakob Disease (CJD)?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問東元電機和哪家公司合併？", 
    "q_en": "Which companies will merge with TECO Group?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問知名漫畫「淘氣阿丹」的創作者是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of famous comic strip Dennis the Menace?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問台灣唯一的一家風箏博物館位於何處？", 
    "q_en": "Where is Taiwan’s only kite museum located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問提出「微晶片的運算能力每18個月會提高1倍」這定律的人是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who proposed the law that computation power of microchips will double every 18 months?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_DISCOVERERS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年在首屆世界電玩賽「世紀帝國II」項目中奪冠的是哪個台灣選手？", 
    "q_en": "Which Taiwanese contestant won the Age of Empires II competition in the first World Cyber Games in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年哪個香港著名八卦雜誌登台，將狗仔偷拍風氣引進台灣？", 
    "q_en": "Which famous Hong Kong tabloid introduced paparazzi into Taiwan in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問世界氣喘日是幾月幾日？", 
    "q_en": "What is the date of the World Asthma Day?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_DATE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年檢察官衝進哪所大學的宿舍搜索學生非法下載MP3？", 
    "q_en": "Which university’s dormitory was examined by prosecutors for students’ illegal downloading of MP3 in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_UNIVERSITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全世界發現的第一個黑嘴端鳳頭燕鷗度冬區是在嘉義縣的哪條溪出海口？", 
    "q_en": "The first ever found habitat of wintering Chinese Crested Tern is located in the inlet of which creek in Chiayi?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_RIVER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問1846年哪個人成功的破譯了貝希斯頓銘文中全部的波斯楔形文字？", 
    "q_en": "Who successfully decoded all the Persian cuneiform writings in the great Behistun inscription in 1846?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問哪位名畫家的兩幅畫「巨人」、「擠牛奶的婦人」被指出可能並非他的真跡？", 
    "q_en": "Which artist’s two paintings, \"the Colossus\" and \"the Milkmaid of Bordeaux,\" were suspected of not being authentic?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年被美國送上火星進行探測任務的是什麼號？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of the spacecraft that was sent by the US to Mars for exploration in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "VEHICLE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全球首位成功登上聖母峰頂的盲人為？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first blind man to reach the summit of Mount Everest?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問創下第一位華人駕駛無動力帆船環繞世界一周紀錄的人是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first Chinese to travel around the world in one week on a non-powered sailboat?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問清朝時，台灣的第一任巡撫是誰?", 
    "q_en": "Who is Taiwan’s first governor in the Ching Dynasty?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問「藍宇」的導演是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the director of Lanyu?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問科魯伊亞火山位於何地？", 
    "q_en": "Where is Kilavea located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_ISLAND"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問紐西蘭的首都是？", 
    "q_en": "What is the capital of New Zealand?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問台北市第一條捷運線木柵線是於民國幾年開始營運？", 
    "q_en": "In what year did Taipei’s first rapid transit route, the Muzha route, commenced in?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問人類史上第一顆鑽石約4000年前在哪裡出土？", 
    "q_en": "Where was the first 4000-year old diamond discovered?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問法國地標艾菲爾鐵塔高幾公尺？", 
    "q_en": "What is the height in meters of the Eiffel Tower?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_HEIGHT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問西元前79年義大利哪座火山爆發，滅亡了龐貝城？", 
    "q_en": "Which volcano’s eruption destroyed the Pompeii in 79BC?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_MOUNTAIN"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問日本漫畫「網球王子」的作者是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of the Japanese comic book “Prince of Tennis”?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問台灣第一座國家公園是？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of Taiwan’s first national park?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問哪個人工衛星捕捉到黑洞的鏡頭？", 
    "q_en": "Which artificial satellite captured photos of a black hole?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "INSTRUMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國哪位總統的政府任命的少數族裔官員是歷來最多的？", 
    "q_en": "Which American president appointed the most officials with minority ethnic background?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問日本NHK每年除夕舉辦的演唱會節目叫什麼名字?", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of Japan’s NHK’s annual new year’s concert?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問被馬友洛環礁包圍的島國為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which island country is surrounded by the Majuro Reef?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問日本漫畫「海賊王」的作者是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is author of the Japanese comic book “One Piece”?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問足球明星大衛貝克漢的妻子是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the wife of the soccer star David Beckham?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問高雄哪一條河原本為臭水，現已整治成功?", 
    "q_en": "Which river in Kaohsiung used to be stinking, but has been renovated successfully?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_RIVER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問泰國最大的島嶼是？", 
    "q_en": "What is the largest island in Thailand?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_ISLAND"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全球規模最大的德國漢諾威CeBIT電腦展中，2001年的最大參展國家是？", 
    "q_en": "What is the biggest participating nation in Cebit, world’s largest computer expo, in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問吳哥窟位於何國境內？", 
    "q_en": "Which country does Angkor War belong to?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "以頭髮當繡線的特殊手工藝起源於中國何朝代？", 
    "q_en": "Which Chinese dynasty started the unique handicraft of hair embroidery?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_RANGE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問現在的哪個地方以前名字為「加蚋仔」？", 
    "q_en": "Which place used to be called \"gara?\"", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問香港在哪一年回歸大陸？", 
    "q_en": "What year did Hong Kong return to China?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問擔任電影「香草的天空」男主角的美國男星是？", 
    "q_en": "Which American star is the main actor of the movie “Vanilla Sky”?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年第34屆世界盃棒球賽在何地舉辦？", 
    "q_en": "Where did the 34th Baseball World Cup take place?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問因搶救美國紐約卡內基音樂廳而留名青史的小提琴大師是？", 
    "q_en": "Which violinist became famous for saving Carnegie Hall in New York?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國和哪個國家首次聯合發行的紀念雙銀幣是為了紀念北美新大陸第一位探險家萊弗艾瑞克？", 
    "q_en": "Which country released the commemorative silver coins in memory of the first explorer of North America Leif Ericson together with the US?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問史上首位踏入伊斯蘭教清真寺的教宗是？", 
    "q_en": "Which pope was the first to enter a Muslim temple?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "亞太安寧緩和醫學學會於何國成立？", 
    "q_en": "In which country was the Asia Pacific Hospice Palliative Care Network, APHN, founded?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年哪個俄羅斯游泳選手把男子100公尺蛙式的世界紀錄推進1分鐘之內？", 
    "q_en": "Which Russian swimmer finished the men’s 100-meter breaststroke within 1 minute in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_RECORD"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "男子100公尺蛙式的世界紀錄是幾秒？", 
    "q_en": "What is the world record time for men’s 100-meter breaststroke?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_DURATION"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年開幕的國立海洋生物博物館位於哪裡？", 
    "q_en": "Where is National Museum of Marine Biology, which commenced in 2000, located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國東北部的居民訂定幾月幾日為「土撥鼠節」？", 
    "q_en": "What date did the residents living in Northeastern US set as the Groundhog Day?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_DATE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問1995年發生的美國奧克拉荷馬市聯邦大樓爆炸案主嫌是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the prime suspect for the bombing of the Murrah Federal Building in Oklahoma City in 1995?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問第一波愛滋病例於西元幾年被公開？", 
    "q_en": "When was the first wave of AIDS publicly disclosed?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問德國通過對二次世界大戰時被納粹政權壓榨的奴工的賠償方案，總金額約多少美金？", 
    "q_en": "What is the amount of indemnity stated in Germany’s act for compensating the laborers who were mistreated under the Nazi regime?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問帶領華盛頓郵報登上財星雜誌五百大的是哪位女性領導人？", 
    "q_en": "Which female leader made the Washington Post appear on Fortune 500?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年發表重大發現的「B介子實驗研究計畫（Belle）」是由哪個國家邀集了14個國家的物理學家共同參與研究？", 
    "q_en": "What country invited physicists from 14 countries to collaborate in the Belle experiment, which publicized major discoveries in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問因為全球暖化海平面上升，位於太平洋上的哪個島國在數十年後有沉入海底的危機？", 
    "q_en": "Which island countries in the Pacific Ocean are in the risk of sinking, because of rising sea level due to global warming?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年在非洲何國挖掘出比早期原人「露西」還要早250萬年左右的原人化石？", 
    "q_en": "In which African country was the primate fossil which was 250 million years older than the primate Lucy unearthed in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問台灣實行已久的大學聯考制度於民國幾年正式走入歷史？", 
    "q_en": "In what year did Taiwan’s Joint College Entrance Examination start?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年哪個人在高雄愛河創造了都市間走鋼索距離最遠的金氏世界紀錄？", 
    "q_en": "Who set the World Guinness Record for high-wire walking the longest distance on the Love River in Kaohsiung in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_RECORD"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年第21屆世界大學運動會（世大運）在何地舉辦？", 
    "q_en": "Where did the 21st Universiade take place in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全台灣年紀最小的大學生是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is Taiwan’s youngest university student?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_RECORD"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問世界最高，有「世界之窗」之稱的建築物是？", 
    "q_en": "What is the world’s tallest building, which is also known as \"Window of the World?\"", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_BUILDING"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「世界之窗」是由哪位日本建築師負責設計？", 
    "q_en": "Which Japanese architect designed the \"Window of the World?\"", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問由盧貝松編劇執導，日本女星廣末涼子和法國男星尚雷諾領銜演出的電影是？", 
    "q_en": "Which movie produced and written by Luc Besson featured Japanese actress Hirosue Ryoko and French actor Jean Reno?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問被譽為本世紀最偉大花腔女高音的人是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the greatest coloratura soprano of the century?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_RECORD"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全球首位進行心臟移植手術的南非醫師是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first doctor, a South African, to perform heart transplant?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問伊斯蘭教的齋戒月是在回曆的幾月？", 
    "q_en": "Which month in the Muslim calendar is the Ramadan?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_MONTH"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問獲得2001年諾貝爾文學獎的作家是？", 
    "q_en": "Which writer won the Nobel Prize in Literature in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "奈波爾是何國的印度裔作家？", 
    "q_en": "What is the Indian writer Naipaul’s country?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問阿富汗的什麼政權因為不願意交出賓拉登而被攻擊以致垮台？", 
    "q_en": "Which Afghanistan regime was annihilated because it refused to hand over Bin Laden?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_POLITICALSYSTEM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問史上第一位女子馬拉松跑進2小時20分紀錄的是哪位日本選手？", 
    "q_en": "Which Japanese female athlete was the first set the record of 2 hours and 20 minutes for marathon competition?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問獅子座流星雨的週期是幾年？", 
    "q_en": "What is the period of the Leo meteor shower?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_FREQUENCY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問台灣第一部平埔族語的辭典是？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of Taiwan’s first Tapani dictionary?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年的世界舉重錦標賽在何地舉行？", 
    "q_en": "Where was the World Weightlifting Championship held in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年的第四屆世界貿易組織部長級會議在何國舉行？", 
    "q_en": "Which country hosted the fourth Ministerial Conference of the World Trade Organization?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問高清愿是哪個集團的總裁？", 
    "q_en": "What corporation is Kao Chin-Yuan the president of?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問紐約市第一位亞裔市議員是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first Chinese-American councilor of New York?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2002年的維也納新年音樂會由哪位著名日本指揮家指揮？", 
    "q_en": "Which Japanese conductor conducted the Vienna Philharmonic's New Years Concert in 2002?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問在歐元未發行之前，土耳其民眾偏好存藏哪國的貨幣？", 
    "q_en": "Which currency did the Turkish like to collect before the release of Euro?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_CURRENCY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問拿到第一個抗血栓蛇毒蛋白美國專利的人是台灣的？", 
    "q_en": "Which Taiwanese has the first US patent on trigramin?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "哪家美國藥廠生產「超級阿斯匹靈」？", 
    "q_en": "Which American drug company produces super-aspirins?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問哪個作家撰寫了「麥田捕手」作者J.D.沙林傑的傳記？", 
    "q_en": "Which writer wrote the biography of Jerome David Salinger, the author of The Catcher in the Rye?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "被禁止出版的沙林傑傳記書名是？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of Salinger biography which was banned?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年德國哪個地區氣溫低達零下45.9度，創下1870年來的新低？", 
    "q_en": "Which German region had temperatures below 45.9 degrees, which was the lowest since 1870, in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2002年冬季奧運會在美國猶他州何地舉行？", 
    "q_en": "Where in Utah was the 2002 Winter Olympics held?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問1960年塞內加爾獨立後的首任總統是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first president of Senegal after its independence in 1960?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問民國87年在台北縣林口弒親案兇手是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the murderer of the family murder case in Linkou, Taipei County in 87?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年獲得亞洲電視節「最佳兒童節目獎」的是公共電視的哪個節目？", 
    "q_en": "Which Taiwan Public Television program won the Asian Television Award in Best Children’s Program?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問獲得2001年曼谷影展「最佳導演獎」的導演？", 
    "q_en": "Who won the Best Director Award in the Bangkok Film Festival of 2001?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "《罪與罰》的作者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of Crime and Punishment?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「民為貴，君為輕」是誰說的？", 
    "q_en": "Who said: \"Commoners are more important than the ruler?\"", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "蓋達組織的首腦是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the leader of Al-Qaeda?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "太平天國的翼王是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the Winged Lord of the Heavenly Kingdom of Great Peace?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "火鳥組曲的作者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of The Firebird Suite?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "世界上第二大的沙漠是哪一個？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of the world's second largest desert?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "世界上最深的湖是那個？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of the world's deepest lake?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_LAKE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "主持建造嘉南大圳的工程師是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Which engineer built the Jianan dajyun?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "玉山有多高？", 
    "q_en": "How tall is Yushan Mountain?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_HEIGHT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "交響曲之父是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the father of symphonies?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_CONTRIBUTOR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "君王論的作者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of The Prince?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "東方主義的作者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of Orientalism?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "法國大革命發生在哪一年？", 
    "q_en": "Which year did the French Revolution take place?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "是誰發現了新大陸？", 
    "q_en": "Who discovered the New World?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_DISCOVERERS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "般若波羅蜜多心經是哪一位大師翻譯的？", 
    "q_en": "Who translated the Prajnaparamita Hrdaya Sutra?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "開羅會議是何時舉行的？", 
    "q_en": "When did the Cairo Conference take place?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "臺灣省第一任巡撫是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is Taiwan's first governor?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "德川幕府的創建者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who started the Tokugawa Shogunate?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "鐵達尼號的導演是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the director of The Titanic?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1960年的美國總統是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the American president in 1960?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "2000年奧運會在哪裡舉辦的？", 
    "q_en": "Where did the 2000 Olympics take place?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "中非共和國的首都在哪？", 
    "q_en": "Where is the capital of the Republic of Central Africa?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "中美斷交是何時發生的？", 
    "q_en": "When did the United States break diplomatic relationship with the Republic of China?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_DATE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "中國的首都在哪裡？", 
    "q_en": "Where is the capital of China?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "中華民國政府何時撤退來台？", 
    "q_en": "When did the Republic of China government retreat to Taiwan?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "中華民國國父是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the father of the Republic of China?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "孔子活了幾歲？", 
    "q_en": "How old was Confucius when he died?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_AGE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "世界上最小的國家是什麼？", 
    "q_en": "Which country is the world's smallest country?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "世界上跑得最快的人？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the world's fastest runner?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_RECORD"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "世界最高的大樓在那個國家？？", 
    "q_en": "Which country has the world's tallest skyscraper?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "台灣人平均壽命幾歲？", 
    "q_en": "What is the average life expectancy of Taiwanese people?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_AGE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "台灣的最北端是哪裡？", 
    "q_en": "What is the northernmost place in Taiwan?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "紅樓夢的作者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of the Dream of the Red Chamber?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "恐龍是什麼時候滅絕的？", 
    "q_en": "When did the dinosaurs go extinct?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_RANGE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "納爾遜在那一年打敗法國的艦隊？", 
    "q_en": "Which year did Nelson defeat the French navy?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "第二次世界大戰在哪一年結束？", 
    "q_en": "Which year did World War II end?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "第二次世界大戰從哪一年開始？", 
    "q_en": "Which year did World War II start?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "奧運的發源地在哪裡？", 
    "q_en": "Where is the originating place of the Olympic?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "網球的發源地是哪裡？", 
    "q_en": "Where is the originating place of tennis?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "羅浮宮在哪個城市？", 
    "q_en": "Which country is the Louvre Museum located in?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年時代華納與哪家公司合併而成為當時美國最大的合併案？", 
    "q_en": "Which corporation bought Time Warner creating the largest company merger in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國聯邦政府以微軟違反何法而判決將其一分為三？", 
    "q_en": "Which law did the District Court Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson said Microsoft violated?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "LAW"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年7月佛羅里達法院判決包括飛利浦‧莫里斯(Philip Morris)在內的美國五大煙草公司應賠償該州共同利害關係人的賠償金額？", 
    "q_en": "How much money has the Miami jury ordered America's big cigarette manufacturers including Philips Morris to pay out for knowingly causing smoking related illnesses in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年因賄選醜聞曝光而遭到國會罷免流亡海外的秘魯總統為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Which Peruvian president went into exile in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "最早發現抗生素的科學家是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first scientist discovering antibiotic?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_DISCOVERERS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "西元2000年美國、以色列、巴勒斯坦三方參與的中東和平對話於何處舉辦？", 
    "q_en": "Where did the President Clinton host meeting between Israeli and Palestinian leadership to address Mideast peace in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問西元2000年奧運的主辦城市為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which city sponsored the millennium Olympic Games?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問西元2000年9月7號台灣參加聯合國一案未列入議程是第幾次叩關失敗？", 
    "q_en": "how many times is it that Taiwan failed in participating in United Nations from the first attempt to 2000?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_ORDER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問西元2000年德國檢方展開政治獻金醜聞調查的對象前總理柯爾曾為何黨黨主席？", 
    "q_en": "Of which party the German's Former Premier Helmut Kohl had been the president?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_POLITICALSYSTEM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問西元2000年7月美方派何人前往北京對TMD以及其他全球戰略佈局與中方展開對話？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the delegate of United States visiting Beijing to negotiate the TMD issue in July, 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年的G8高峰會在日本何地舉行？", 
    "q_en": "Which city hosted the G8 summit in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問芬蘭第一位女總統為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the Finland's first woman president?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年沉沒於北極圈巴倫支海的俄羅斯核子潛艇的名字？", 
    "q_en": "Which Russian nuclear submarine sank in the Barents Sea in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "VEHICLE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問涉嫌竊取美國洛薩拉摩斯實驗室核武機密的華裔科學家為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was accused of violating Atomic Energy Act because of his purportedly mishandling restricted data of Los Alamos National Laboratories in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年NBA總冠軍賽最有價值球員為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the MVP of NBA Finals 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年柏林影展金熊獎得獎作品為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which film won the Golden Bear award in Berlin Film Festival 2000?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問第72屆奧斯卡金像獎最佳影片是哪一部電影？", 
    "q_en": "Which film won the best picture at 72nd Academy Awards (Oscars 2000)?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國驅逐艦寇爾號於何國港口遭到恐怖份子以炸彈小艇攻擊？", 
    "q_en": "Where was the American destroyer Cole bombed in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年率團訪問北韓的美國國務卿為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the secretary of State of United States visiting North Korea in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年肆虐全球的「我愛你」電腦病毒為何國學生所撰寫？", 
    "q_en": "Which country did the computer virus \"I love you\" come from", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年初全球七大工業國的財政首長與央行總裁會議於何地舉行？", 
    "q_en": "Which city hosted the G7 finance ministers and central bank governors meeting in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國於哪位總統任內通過給予中國永久性正常貿易關係的法案？", 
    "q_en": "Which president of United States granted China permanent normal trade relation (PNTR)?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問東帝汶獨立建國過程中的最重要的民運領袖為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the leader fighting for independence of East Timor?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問智利於1973~1990實行獨裁統治的右翼軍政府領袖為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the leader of the right wing military government in Chile from 1973 to 1990?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問日本軟體銀行的創辦人為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the president of Softbank Corporation?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問收購南韓三星汽車的外國廠商為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which corporation bought South Korea's Samsung Motors?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年墨西哥總統大選當選人為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the winner of the Mexican presidential election in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年俄羅斯新任總統為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the winner of the Russian presidential election in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問世界上第一個將安樂死合法化的國家？", 
    "q_en": "Which country is the first country in the world to legalize euthanasia?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "第一位當選參議員的美國第一夫人是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first U.S. First lady Senator?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年的資訊科技大會在何地舉辦？", 
    "q_en": "Which city hosted the World Congress on Information Technology (WCIT) in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年底負責籌組新內閣的印尼副總統為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is in charge of Indonesia's cabinet in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年全球造成最多人遷徙的水患主要發生在何國？", 
    "q_en": "Which country in Africa is attacked by severe floods which devastated almost whole country?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問狂牛症最早起源於何國？", 
    "q_en": "Which country is the mad cow disease originated from?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問法國航空公司協和號有史以來第一次空難於何處墜毀？", 
    "q_en": "Which city did the Concorde crash first?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問前南斯拉夫前總統米洛謝維契共統治南斯拉夫幾年？", 
    "q_en": "How many years did the former Yugoslavian former president Milo Hsiehwei rule the country?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_DURATION"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "參加兩韓高峰會的北韓領導人是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the leader of North Korea taking part in the Korean Summit?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年歐洲國家杯冠軍隊為？", 
    "q_en": "Which country won Euro 2000 crown?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問南韓第一大民營建造商為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which firm is the largest construction company in South Korea?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年台灣總統當選人是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the winner of the Taiwan presidential election in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年台灣副總統當選人是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the winner of the Taiwan vice-presidential election in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問聯合國總部在哪一座城市？", 
    "q_en": "Which city does United Nations locate its headquarter?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年大衛營以巴和談破裂的主因乃是肇因於哪個城市的主權爭議？", 
    "q_en": "Which city's jurisdictional dispute does cause the Israeli and Palestine peace talks which conducts in Camp David to burst?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年遭到國會彈劾下臺的菲律賓總統為誰？", 
    "q_en": "who was the Philippine president encountering Congress impeaches to leave office in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問首次搭載太空觀光客進駐國際太空站(ISS)之俄國太空船為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which Russian space ship did first embark space tourist to International Space Station (ISS)?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "VEHICLE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "哪一間日本公司設計飛行速率二馬赫的新飛機?", 
    "q_en": "Which corporation in Japan designed new aircraft to travel at Mach 2?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年瑪丹娜與誰結婚？", 
    "q_en": "Who is Madonna married to in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "誰是第一位自費太空觀光客？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first space tourist?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2000年世界最佳男運動員為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who in 2000 is the world best male athlete?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "西班牙境內的分離運動組織為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which group in Spain supported separation movement?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_POLITICALSYSTEM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "一級方程式賽車冠軍車手為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the champion at the Formula 1 World Championship?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "西元2000年加入奧地利聯合政府的自由黨黨魁是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the leader of Freedom Party joining the Austria coalition government in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "華語片臥虎藏龍之導演為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the director of the Chinese movie crouching tiger, hidden dragon?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "2000年木村拓哉宣布結婚之對象為誰？", 
    "q_en": "To whom is Mr. Takuya Kimura married in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "哈利波特系列小說之作者為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of the series novel \"Harry Porter\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "2000年諾貝爾文學獎的獲獎者為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the winner of the 2000 Nobel Prize in Literature?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "2000年諾貝爾文學獎的獲獎作品為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which work is the winner of the 2000 Nobel Prize in Literature?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "七大工業國(G7)中最先與北韓建交者為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which in the G7 is the first country to establish diplomatic relations with North Korea?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "遭指控涉嫌犯下雞姦案的前馬來西亞副總理為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the Former Malaysian Deputy Premier convicted of sodomy?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "二次世界大戰中日本在位天皇為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the emperor of Japan in World War II?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「中國物理學之父」是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the \"father of the Chinese physics\"", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_CONTRIBUTOR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "世界經濟論壇設於何國？", 
    "q_en": "Where is the World Economic Forum located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "美國第一家申請發行網際網路股票的報社是哪一家？", 
    "q_en": "Which newspaper agency is the first one to apply for the release Internet stock in United States?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "聯合國祕書長是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the Secretary General of United Nations?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "創作出連環漫畫「史努比」的插畫家是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the painter creating the series cartoon \"Snoopy\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "何大一博士研發的「雞尾酒療法」是為了治療哪種疾病？", 
    "q_en": "Which kind of disease does Dr. David Ho research and develop \"the cocktail therapy\" for?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "DISEASE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "著名的莫高窟位於中國大陸何處？", 
    "q_en": "Where is the famous Mogao Caves located in mainland China?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "哪位日本首相因「神國論」而引發日本朝野的不滿？", 
    "q_en": "Which Japanese prime minister initiated the disaffection of the government and the people because of his talks of \"divine nation\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "比薩斜塔位於何國？", 
    "q_en": "Which country is the Leaning Tower of Pisa located in?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "誰發動西安事變？", 
    "q_en": "Who starts the Xi'an Incident?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "誰在西安事變被挾持？", 
    "q_en": "Who is captured and detained in the Xi'an Incident?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "張學良晚年住在何處？", 
    "q_en": "Where did Zhang Xueliang live in his old age?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "韓戰爆發於哪一年？", 
    "q_en": "When did the Korean War take place?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "韓戰停戰協定簽署於哪一年？", 
    "q_en": "When was the ceasefire agreement for Korean War signed?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "誰是「自由軟體之父」？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the \"father of free software\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_CONTRIBUTOR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "哪個國家的人民最長壽？", 
    "q_en": "Which country has the greatest longevity in the world?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "2000年哪個德國城市舉辦的萬國博覽會？", 
    "q_en": "Which city in Germany hosted World Exposition 2000?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "誰嫁給麥克道格拉斯？", 
    "q_en": "To whom is Michael Douglas married?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "何種氣體高度集中會造成溫室效應？", 
    "q_en": "Which gas with high degree of concentration will create the greenhouse effect?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "SUBSTANCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "誰被稱為「預力混凝土先生」？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the \"Mr. Prestressed Concrete\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "第六次2000年全球氣候會議在哪個城市舉行？", 
    "q_en": "Which city hosted the 6th Conference of the Parties (COP) 2000?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "第七屆西太平洋化療及傳染病醫學會議在哪個城市舉行？", 
    "q_en": "Which city hosted the 7th West Pacific Ocean Chemotherapy and Infectious Disease Medicine Conference?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "知名建築「落水山莊」是由哪位建築師所設計的？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the architect of the well-known building \"Falling water\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "創造出知名偵探人物「福爾摩斯」的作者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who created the famous fictional detectives \"Sherlock Holmes\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "第一次世界大戰於西元幾年爆發？", 
    "q_en": "When did the World War I take place?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "愛迪生在哪一年發明電燈？", 
    "q_en": "When did Thomas Edison invent the light bulb?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "科學家第一次成功複製哺乳動物是在西元幾年？", 
    "q_en": "When did the scientist first successfully duplicate mammals?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "英國的第三個海峽殖民地是哪裡？", 
    "q_en": "Where is the third straits settlements of Great Britain?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "帛琉共和國於西元幾年獨立？", 
    "q_en": "When has Palau been an independent country?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "2000年第53屆坎城影展影后是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the winner of the Best Actress Award in Cannes 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "被稱為日本精神象徵的山是哪一座山？", 
    "q_en": "Which mountain has been regarded as the spiritual symbol of Japan?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_MOUNTAIN"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "蒙古何時成為獨立國家？", 
    "q_en": "When has Mongolia been an independent country?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "第三屆東亞運動會在哪一個城市舉辦？", 
    "q_en": "Which city hosted the 3rd East Asian Games?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "哪一部電影榮獲2000年第53屆坎城影展金棕櫚獎？", 
    "q_en": "Which film took the Palme d'Or Award in Cannes 2000?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "全世界種植基因改造農作物的土地面積排名第三的國家是哪一國？", 
    "q_en": "Which country ranked the third in land area of gene transformation crops?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "2000年第53屆坎城影展影帝是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the winner of the Best Actor Award in Cannes 2000?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "著名的法國區位於美國的哪一個城市？", 
    "q_en": "Which city of United States is the well-known \"French Quarter\" located in?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "著名的「自由女神」位於美國的哪一個城市？", 
    "q_en": "Which city of United States is the well-known \"Statue of Liberty\" located in?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "參加兩韓高峰會的南韓領導人是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the leader of South Korea taking part in the Korean Summit?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1989年天安門民運時的中共總書記是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the General Secretary of the Central Committee of Communist Party of China in Tiananmen Square protests of 1989?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "西遊記的作者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of \"Journey to the West\" (Money King)?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "中國的三星堆遺址於何省？", 
    "q_en": "Where is the Sanxingdui remains located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "口袋怪獸在美國的哪一個城市首先開賣？", 
    "q_en": "Where was the first city in United States to sell \"pocket monsters\"?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "個人化郵票起源於何年？", 
    "q_en": "When did the personalized stamps first appear?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "第十三屆富士通杯國際圍棋賽優勝獎金是多少？", 
    "q_en": "When did the personalized stamps appear?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「拉麵博物館」在日本哪一個城市？", 
    "q_en": "Which city in Japan is the \"La Men Museum\" located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "歐洲最佳經商程式是哪一個城市？", 
    "q_en": "Which city is the best European city for commerce?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "台灣任期最長的中央銀行總裁是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the Taiwan's Central Bank Governor with longest tenure?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "哪一國是全球最適合居住的國家？", 
    "q_en": "Which country is the most suitable for people to live?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "榮獲諾貝爾和平獎的南韓總統是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Which South Korean president was the winner of the Nobel Prize in Peace?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  },
  {
    "q_zh": "歷史上死難人數最多的沉船是哪一艘？", 
    "q_en": "Which sunken wreck caused the most people died in the history?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "VEHICLE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "艾森豪何時就任總統？", 
    "q_en": "When did President Eisenhower take office?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "巴斯克分離運動領袖是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the leader of Basque Separatist Group ETA?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本新幹線何時開始營運？", 
    "q_en": "When did Japan's Shin-gan-shen (Bullet Train) start transportation business?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "美國食品藥物管理局在2000年核准新的抗生素為何？", 
    "q_en": "What was the name of a new antibiotic approved by FDA in 2000?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRODUCT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "那個城市是法國亞爾薩斯的首府？", 
    "q_en": "Which city is the capital of Alsace, France?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "駱馬的壽命大約幾年？", 
    "q_en": "How many years is Llama's life approximately?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_AGE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "阿波丸輪船何時沈沒？", 
    "q_en": "When did the Awa Maru steamboat sink?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "太平洋戰爭發生於何年？", 
    "q_en": "When did the Pacific War take place?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "拿破崙於何年發動政變，取得政權？", 
    "q_en": "When did Napoleon start the coup d'etat and obtain the political power?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "拿破崙出生於何地？", 
    "q_en": "Where was Napoleon born?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_ISLAND"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "DB2資料庫管理軟體是哪一個公司的產品？", 
    "q_en": "Which company issued DB2 Database Management Software?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "IEEE 1394的傳輸速率為多少？", 
    "q_en": "How many is the transfer rate of IEEE 1394?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_FREQUENCY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "Gunn Report根據全球重要廣告獎項競賽得獎統計，公布2000年表現最佳的廣告代理商是哪一家公司？", 
    "q_en": "According to the results of some global commercial advertisement competitions, which company was ranking on the first place by Gunn Report in 2000", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "惠普科技比照航空公司累積里程數的概念，推出的消費獎勵計畫名稱是什麼？", 
    "q_en": "What's the name of the reward program announced by HP which concept was the same as the airline's reward plan?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "聯合線上、ShopIBM合辦的網路尋恩人活動名稱為何？", 
    "q_en": "What's name of the program which topic was to looking for the person you want to thank through the internet that provided by udn.com and ShopIBM?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "率先推出台灣手機保單的公司是哪個？", 
    "q_en": "Which company provide the first cell phone insurance program in Taiwan?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "奈比特因為製作哪個節目，而獲得一九九九年Rolex獎？", 
    "q_en": "Peter Knights won the 1999 Rolex award by producing which program?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "前往墨西哥進行共同合作繁衍計劃的日本熊貓叫什麼名字？", 
    "q_en": "What's the name of the panda that be sent by the joint breeding plan from Japan to Mexico?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ANIMAL"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "一九０一年紐西蘭推動成立「旅客與休閒勝地部門」的首相是誰？", 
    "q_en": "What's the name of the New Zealand's prime minister who push to establish the Department of Tourist and Health Resorts in 1901?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "當人體內的銅代謝異常時，會造成哪個疾病？", 
    "q_en": "What's name of the disease When human body can't metabolism copper normally?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "DISEASE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "全省第一個自訂有電力設施空汙標準的縣市是哪個？", 
    "q_en": "Which county is the first to set the electric facilities air pollution standard in Taiwan?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "蘭吉和他的兒子，於西元 1845 年和薩克索尼（SAXONY）州政府簽訂合約，在哪裡創辦製表工廠？", 
    "q_en": "Where was Ferdinand Adolph Lange and his son signed the contract with Saxony State Government to establish a watch factory in 1845?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "台灣卅個山地鄉第一本原住民鄉志，是哪個？", 
    "q_en": "What's the name of the first aboriginal chorography of the 30 aboriginal county in Taiwan?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "陳水扁總統將軍禮歡迎儀式首度移師南台灣擴大舉行，是為了歡迎哪個來訪國家的元首？", 
    "q_en": "To welcome which country's leader that President Chen, Shui-bian first hold the military honors ceremony in Southern Taiwan?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "野生救援組織執行長奈比特指稱全球消費鯨鯊最多的是哪個國家？", 
    "q_en": "Which country that Peter Knights, the CEO of WildAid accused to consume the whale and shark most?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "微軟提供網路使用者自行選擇隱私保護的系統叫什麼？", 
    "q_en": "Name the personal Internet private protection system by Microsoft.", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "威爾遜氏病是因為人體內哪個元素代謝異常？", 
    "q_en": "Which element that human body can't metabolism normally caused the Wilson's disease?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "SUBSTANCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "指稱台灣是全球消費鯨鯊最多的國家的野生救援組織執行長叫什麼名字？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the CEO of WildAid that accused Taiwan to consume the whale and shark most?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "誰於西元 1845 年和薩克索尼州政府簽訂合約，在格拉蘇帝創辦製表工廠？", 
    "q_en": "Who signed the contract with Saxony State Government to establish a watch factory at Glashutte in 1845?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「無法無家」這部電影的導演是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the director of the film named \"Sans Toit NiLoi\" in 1985?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "首先提供網路使用者自行選擇隱私保護的系統的是哪一些公司？", 
    "q_en": "Which company provided the first personal Internet private protection system called \"P3P\"?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "美國航空暨太空總署計畫在二００四年三月發射到水星探險的太空船名稱是什麼？", 
    "q_en": "What's the name of the space ship launched by NASA to Mercury in March 2004?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "VEHICLE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "根據NOMOS的創辦者RONALD SCHWERTNER，能夠在腕表上標示格拉蘇帝的有多少個品牌？", 
    "q_en": "According to the founder of Nomos, how many watch brands can mark \"Glashutte\" on their products?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "電影Intimacy《親密》，是改編自何人的原著小說？", 
    "q_en": "The film called \"Intimacy\" was based on whose original fiction?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "和美國空軍偵察機EP-3發生碰撞的和中國戰鬥機名稱為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the Chinese fighter that collided with U.S. Navy surveillance plane called?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "VEHICLE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "在美國洛杉磯出版台灣現代文學系列的是哪個出版社？", 
    "q_en": "Which company publish \"The Taiwanese Modern\" series in Los Angeles?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001印度大地震受創最嚴重的省份為？", 
    "q_en": "Which province of India was devastated by the Indian Earthquake in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問九一一恐怖攻擊過後全球陷入哪一種細菌的恐怖攻擊疑雲中？", 
    "q_en": "After 911, the whole world was under the strain of what kind of bacteria?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "DISEASE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問前南斯拉夫總統米洛謝維契曾因發動哪一場戰爭而遭到美國與北約空襲懲罰？", 
    "q_en": "Which war started by Yugoslavia ex-president Milosevic triggered the air attack by the United States and the United Nations as a punishment?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "AFFAIR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年亞洲第一起確定狂牛症病例發生在何國？", 
    "q_en": "Which country had the first confirmed case of mad cow disease ever found in Asia, 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年贏得環法自由車賽完成三連霸的美國抗癌車手為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Which American cancer-fighting bicycler won his third straight in Tour de France?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問惠普科技於2001年宣布合併哪一家電腦大廠？", 
    "q_en": "Which computer company did Hewlett-Packard announced to merge with?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國史上第一位華裔部長為誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first Chinese minister in the history of the US?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問神學士政權摧毀的兩尊巨佛雕像位於阿富汗境內何省？", 
    "q_en": "The two Buddhas destroyed by Taliban were located in which province of Afghanistan?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問與中國戰機擦撞並迫降於海南島的美國偵察機為何型號？", 
    "q_en": "Which kind was the American spy plane colliding with a Chinese fighter and landed on Hainan?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "VEHICLE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問審核通過爭議性中學歷史教科書的日本政府單位為何？", 
    "q_en": "Which Japanese governmental office approved the controversial history textbook for high schools?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_POLITICALSYSTEM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年美國聯準會(Fed)共降息幾次？", 
    "q_en": "How many times did Fed cut interest rates in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問抗憂鬱症藥物百憂解(Prozac)由哪一家藥廠研發？", 
    "q_en": "Which company produces the antidepressant Prozac?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年第58屆金球獎茱莉亞羅勃玆(Julia Roberts)以何部片贏得最佳劇情片女主角？", 
    "q_en": "By which movie did Julia Roberts won the 58th Goldeb Globe Award for the best actress in a leading role -- drama, in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問漢他病毒主要的宿主是何種動物，並會經其傳染給人類？", 
    "q_en": "What kind of animals is the host of Hanta virus?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ANIMAL"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年哪位大陸人士因表演隔空抓藥的特異功能並替人看診，有詐欺和違反醫師法之嫌而遭到台北地檢署起訴？", 
    "q_en": "Which person from Mainland China was accused of fraud and violation of the Doctor's Law by the Taipei District Public Prosecutors Office because of her performance of supernatural power to conjure up medicine pills out of thin air and providing medical treatment?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問中美洲面積最小的國家為？", 
    "q_en": "What is the smallest country in Central America?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年四月首度在台北舉行的阿格麗希音樂節是以哪國籍的著名鋼琴家阿格麗希(Martha Argerich)為名？", 
    "q_en": "What is the nationality of the famous pianist Martha Argerich?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問於2001年停刊，號稱為台灣第一家網路原生報的報紙為？", 
    "q_en": "What was the newspaper, known as the first online-only newspaper in Taiwan, which was shut down in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年第51屆柏林影展獲得「最佳新人獎」的女星是？", 
    "q_en": "Who won the Piper Heidsieck New Talent Award to Best Young Actress in the 51st Berlin Film Festival?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問因為何種因素，使亞洲成為抗藥性細菌的最大發源地？", 
    "q_en": "What reason makes Asia the greatest birthplace of antibiotic-resistant bacteria?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "REASON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問南韓哪個集團的創辦人金宇中因為涉及詐欺潛逃國外成為逃犯？", 
    "q_en": "Kim Woo-Choong, a Korean fugitive being accused of fraud, was the founder of which group?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問首位加入美國NBA的華人球員是？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the first Chinese player in the NBA?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問人類書寫的起源是源自哪個文明？", 
    "q_en": "Writing of human beings originated in which culture?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問與新加坡碧山大巴窯締結姊妹區，是台北市第二個進行跨國交流的行政區為？", 
    "q_en": "Which district became the sister district of Bishan Toa Payoh, Singapore, and became the second district having international relations in Taipei?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問284年才出現一次的天文奇景「熒惑守心」是火星和哪個星座的主星心宿二非常接近並一起散發紅色艷光？", 
    "q_en": "The astronomical spectacle happening once in 284 years was the conjunctione of Mars and the alpha of which constellation, Antares?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "NATURE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問日本有史以來的第一位女性外務大臣是？", 
    "q_en": "Who became the first female Minister of Foreign Affairs in Japan?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問獲選為2001年全球最佳機場的是哪個機場？", 
    "q_en": "Which airport was voted as the world's best airport in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_BUILDING"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問行動電話知名廠商易利信(Ericsson)和日本的哪家公司合資組成行動通訊公司？", 
    "q_en": "The famous mobile phone company Ericsson have merged with which company into a joint venture of mobile phone businesses?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全球首度認可同性婚姻的是那個國家？", 
    "q_en": "What is the first country permitting homosexual marriage?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問哪種保育鳥類因為多出現在台南縣的菱角田中，而有「菱角鳥」之稱？", 
    "q_en": "Which conservative species of birds is named as a \"bird of the water chestnut\" because its perching in ponds of water chestnuts in Tainan, Taiwan?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ANIMAL"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問哪種水果有消除緊張、抗憂鬱的作用？", 
    "q_en": "Which kind of fruit can reduce tension and depression?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "FOOD"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年3月第一家麥當勞飯店在何國成立？", 
    "q_en": "The first MacDonald Hotel was built in which country in March, 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問俗稱「玉婆」的伊麗莎白泰勒(Elizabeth Taylor)曾結過幾次婚？", 
    "q_en": "How many times did Elizabeth Taylor got married?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問日本漫畫「亂馬1/2」的作者是？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of Japanese comic \"Ranma 1/2\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問紅樓夢的作者是？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the author of \"Dreams of the Red Chamber\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全球第一座國家公園是？", 
    "q_en": "What is the first national park in the world?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問在宮崎駿的電影「神隱少女」中，女主角千尋的父母因為吃了要給神靈的貢品而變成了什麼動物？", 
    "q_en": "In the Hayao Miyazaki's movie \"Spirited Away\", Chihiro's parents ate offering to gods then turned into what kind of animal?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ANIMAL"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全世界人類喝的最多、僅次於水的飲料是？", 
    "q_en": "What is the most-often drunk beverages ranking only next to water?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "FOOD"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問台北市因為什麼效應，會使地震波有放大效果？", 
    "q_en": "What effect magnified the earthquake in Taipei?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "NATURE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年的英國大選中，布萊爾所領導的哪個黨再次獲勝？", 
    "q_en": "Which party was lead by Blair to a winning of the British General Election in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_POLITICALSYSTEM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1999年發生美國9歲女孩吃椰果果凍噎住變成植物人的意外，請問她的家屬為此控告哪家食品公司？", 
    "q_en": "Which food company was accused by the relatives of the 9-year-old American girl who was choked when eating a Konjac Mini Gel Snack and fell into a vegetative state in 1999?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_COMPANY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問2001年世界飛盤全能賽在何地舉辦？", 
    "q_en": "Where did the World Overall Championships of the World Flying Disc Federation take place in 2001?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問華盛頓郵報在1970年代曾因為刊載哪件總統弊案而聲名大噪？", 
    "q_en": "Washington Post became famous because of their reporting of what presidential scandal?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "AFFAIR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問國際標準的新生兒女男比是多少(幾個女生：幾個男生)？", 
    "q_en": "What is the worldwide statistical norm of female-to-male ratio at birth?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_RATE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問美國前總統雷根罹患了老人失智症中的哪一種？", 
    "q_en": "Which senile dementia did Ronald Reagan, the former president of the US, suffer from?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "DISEASE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問1997年以「雷射致冷捕捉原子」的研究成果獲得諾貝爾物理獎的華裔科學家是？", 
    "q_en": "Which Chinese science won the Nobel Prize in Physics in 1997 for \"development of methods to cool and trap atoms with laser light\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問九一一恐怖攻擊事件的主謀是哪個人？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the prime suspect behind the 911 attack?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問九一一之後，繼美國之後第二個被證實有炭疽熱病例的國家是？", 
    "q_en": "After the US, what was the second country in which positive anthrax infection was reported after 911 attack?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問1998年的諾貝爾醫學獎得主是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the winner of the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine in 1998?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問哪個芬蘭人因為個人興趣而寫出了Linux作業系統的原型？", 
    "q_en": "Which Finnish wrote the prototype of Linux for his personal hobby?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請問全球首位獲得「世界和平獎」殊榮的女性是？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the first female winning the World Peace prize?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "誰是日本阿爾卑斯山之父？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the \"Father of the Nihon Arupusu\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_CONTRIBUTOR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "哪一本書最早提到「日本阿爾卑斯山」這個名詞？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the book in which a term \"The Japanese Alps\" first appeared?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "有多少比率的受訪者表示他們願意在20世紀末來臨前和伴侶一起旅行？", 
    "q_en": "What percent of respondents said they wanted to travel with their spouses before the end of the 20th century?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "史努比最早出現在哪個連環漫畫中？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the comic strip where Snoopy made his debut?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "美國第二十六任總統是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the 26th U.S. president?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「日本中部及北部旅遊指南」這本書何時出版？", 
    "q_en": "When was \"A Handbook for Travellers in Central and Northern Japan\" published?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請列出安德烈‧華依達的作品。", 
    "q_en": "Name the works by Andrzej Wajda.", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "安德烈‧華依達曾獲得奧斯卡所頒發的什麼獎項？", 
    "q_en": "What award was Andrzej Wajda given at the Academy Awards ceremony?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRIZE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "由胡德森‧西華博士所成立的組織名稱為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of the organization established by Prof. Hudson de Silva?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "國際眼庫曾提供多少個眼角膜到日本？", 
    "q_en": "What is the number of corneas provided by the International Eye Bank Association to Japan?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1600年時，漂流到臼杵岸上的荷蘭船隻名稱為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of the Dutch ship that drifted ashore at Usuki in 1600?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "VEHICLE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "關原合戰發生於何時？", 
    "q_en": "When did the Battle of Sekigahara begin?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "田中澄江八十八歲大壽是哪時候？", 
    "q_en": "When did Sumie Tanaka turn 88?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "世界最早運行的地下鐵在哪裡？", 
    "q_en": "Where did the world's first subway start its operation?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "自從世界最早的地下鐵在倫敦運行後，距今多少年？", 
    "q_en": "How long has it been since the world's first subway made its debut in London?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_DURATION"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "在便利商店影印一張要多少日圓？", 
    "q_en": "How much do convenience stores charge for a photocopy?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "濱崎紘一所寫的書，書名為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the book written by Koichi Hamazaki?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "菅谷昭所寫的書，書名為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the book written by Akira Suganoya?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "青蛙專用隧道位於何處？", 
    "q_en": "Where are tunnels for frogs located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "卑彌呼女皇生前要求將她葬在何處？", 
    "q_en": "Where is Princess Yamato Totobi-Momoso said to be buried?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_BUILDING"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "有關箸墓的故事是記載在哪本書上？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the book where the story of Hashi tomb appears?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "埋葬在箸墓內的是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who are possibly buried in the Hashi tomb?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「九段地區櫻花街道」的出版者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who publishes Kudan Kaiwai Sakura Michi?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "有珠山和十勝地區距離多遠？", 
    "q_en": "What is the distance between Mt. Usu and the Tokachi area?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_LENGTH"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "皮納吐坡火山位於何處？", 
    "q_en": "Where is Mt. Pinatubo located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_COUNTRY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "武田澄江的祖父是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the grandfather of Sumie Takeda?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "有多少年輕人曾經參加Sadako營隊活動？", 
    "q_en": "How many young people have taken part in Camp Sadako?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "新渡戶稻造所寫的英文書書名為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the book written in English by Inazo Nitobe?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "新渡戶稻造是哪裡人？", 
    "q_en": "Where does Inazo Nitobe come from?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "建立南京政府的是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who established the Nanjing government?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "蔣介石逝世於何時？", 
    "q_en": "When did Chiang Kai-shek die?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_DATE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "黑澤明1963年所執導的電影，片名為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the film directed by Akira Kurosawa in 1963?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "二次世界大戰後至今，日本發生多少件綁票勒贖的案件？", 
    "q_en": "How many kidnapping for ransom cases have there been since the end of WWII?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1986年讀賣新聞的民調中，支持修改憲法者的比率有多少？", 
    "q_en": "What percent of respondents in a 1986 survey conducted by Yomiuri Shimbun favored revising the Constitution?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1993年讀賣新聞的民調中，贊成修改憲法者的比率有多少？", 
    "q_en": "According to the results of a Yomiuri Shimbun survey in 1993, what percent of respondents said they favored revising the Constitution?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「法之華三法行」教團向信徒募集到多少日圓？", 
    "q_en": "How much has Ho-no-Hana Sampogyo collected from its followers?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "到現在還有多少鄉鎮市仍有兒童歌舞伎的表演？", 
    "q_en": "In how many municipalities is kodomo kabuki still performed?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「安宅之關」一幕，出現在哪一齣歌舞伎中？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the kabuki play where there is a scene at \"Atakanoseki\"?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "淺間神社位在東京哪一區？", 
    "q_en": "In which ward is Sengen Shrine located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "阿波丸號是在一天當中的什麼時候，被美國潛艇擊沈？", 
    "q_en": "At what time of day was the Awa Maru torpedoed and sunk by a U.S. submarine?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_TIME"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "阿波丸號事件中，有多少人死亡？", 
    "q_en": "How many people were killed in the Awa Maru case?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "羅傑‧迪格曼所寫有關阿波丸號事件的書，書名為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the book written by Roger Dingman about the Awa Maru case?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「阿波丸擊沈」一書的作者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the author of \"Ghost of War--the Sinking of the Awa Maru and Japanese-American relations, 1945-95\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "每年大約有多少人因交通事故而死亡？", 
    "q_en": "About how many people are killed in traffic accidents every year?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本國內每年大概有多少貓狗被人道處死？", 
    "q_en": "How many dogs and cats are exterminated annually in Japan?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請舉出一本康拉德‧勞倫茲博士所寫的書。", 
    "q_en": "Name a book by Dr. Konrad Loren.", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "Monotsukuri大學預定招生名額是多少？", 
    "q_en": "How many students will be admitted to Monotsukuri Daigaku?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本富山縣山田村超過六十五歲的老人佔村民人口的百分之多少？", 
    "q_en": "What percent of villagers in Yamadamura of Toyama Prefecture are 65 years old or older?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本富山縣山田村擁有個人電腦的家戶比率為何？", 
    "q_en": "What percent of households own personal computers in Yamadamura, Toyama Prefecture?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "小原乃梨子在「哆啦Ａ夢」中為哪個角色配音？", 
    "q_en": "Whose role does Noriko Ohara play in \"Doraemon\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "2002年世界杯足球賽決賽最便宜的門票要多少日圓？", 
    "q_en": "What will be the lowest price of a ticket for the 2002 World Cup soccer finals?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "2002年世界杯足球賽決賽最貴的門票要多少日圓？", 
    "q_en": "What will be the highest price of a ticket for the 2002 World Cup soccer finals?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "2002年世界杯足球賽決賽電視轉播權利金是前幾屆的幾倍？", 
    "q_en": "How many times higher will the broadcasting rights for the 2002 World Cup soccer finals be than those for the previous World Cup?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "安東尼‧聖艾修伯里寫過什麼書？", 
    "q_en": "What did Antoine de Saint-Exupery write?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1900年6月29日出生於法國里昂的作家是誰？", 
    "q_en": "What writer was born in Lyon on June 29, 1900?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "植物學家牧野先生於1953年所出版的文集名稱為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the essay written by Mr. Makino, a botanist, in 1953?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "哪一本書有繡球花最早被介紹至日本的記載？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the book that introduced hydrangea to Japan?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "山本武臣所編有關繡球花的書，書名是什麼？", 
    "q_en": "What is the book about hydrangea compiled by Takeomi Yamamoto called?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "靠近日本三宅島大路池的遺跡，名稱為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of the relic near the Tairoike lake?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_BUILDING"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "今年除草十字軍活動何時開始？", 
    "q_en": "When will the Saviors of the Forest project start this year?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_DATE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "想知道除草十字軍活動相關詳細資料，應該詢問哪個單位？", 
    "q_en": "Who is to be contacted for more information about the Saviors of the Forest project?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "勞拉‧史賓塞每年從哈佛獲得多少美元的獎學金？", 
    "q_en": "What is the annual amount of the scholarship given to Laura Spence by Harvard?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "金日成的繼承人是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who took Kim Il Sung's chair as his successor?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1929年在墨西哥創立的政黨名稱為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of a political party established in 1929 in Mexico?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_POLITICALSYSTEM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "在日本執政長達三十八年的是哪個政黨？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of a party that dominated politics in Japan for 38 years?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_POLITICALSYSTEM"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "沖繩高峰會的會場在哪裡？", 
    "q_en": "Where is the Okinawa summit held?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_BUILDING"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "英國船隻何時擱淺在沖繩北谷町海岸邊？", 
    "q_en": "When did a British vessel run aground on a beach in Chatan-cho, Okinawa?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "荷蘭墓地內埋葬了多少個外國人？", 
    "q_en": "How many foreigners have been laid to rest at Holland grave?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_COUNT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本有多少比率的高中學校到海外進行修業旅行？", 
    "q_en": "What percent of Japanese high schools travel abroad for their school trips?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "SOGO百貨的前身—大和屋，開業於何時？", 
    "q_en": "When was Yamatoya, Sogo's predecessor, opened?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "誰是大阪船場大和屋的老闆？", 
    "q_en": "Who was the owner of Yamatoya in Senba, Osaka?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_LEADER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1997年日本全國未繳納之消費稅額有多少日圓？", 
    "q_en": "What was the amount of retained consumption tax in fiscal 1997?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1998年日本全國未繳納之消費稅額有多少日圓？", 
    "q_en": "What was the amount of retained consumption tax in fiscal 1998?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本現存最古老的中文詩集是哪一本？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of Japan's oldest Chinese poetry collection in existence?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本皇太后下葬於何處？", 
    "q_en": "Where was the Empress Dowager laid to sleep?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_BUILDING"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "二次世界大戰前，日本帝國大學在最顛峰時期，有多少比率的課程有實際開課？", 
    "q_en": "At best, what percent of scheduled classes were actually taught in Japan's imperial universities before the World War II?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本「全國免洗筷高峰會」將在哪裡舉行？", 
    "q_en": "Where will the National Disposable Chopsticks Summit be held?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本第一屆「全國免洗筷高峰會」於何時舉辦？", 
    "q_en": "When was the first National Disposable Chopsticks Summit held?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「獵殺紅色十月」的作者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who wrote \"The Hunt for Red October\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "目前東京大學規定的退休年紀是幾歲？", 
    "q_en": "What is the retirement age at Tokyo University?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_AGE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "俄國核子潛艇庫爾斯克號，是在一天當中的哪個時候沈沒？", 
    "q_en": "At what time of day did the nuclear submarine Kursk sink?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_TIME"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "和戴安娜王妃一起在車禍中死亡的她的男朋友叫什麼名字？", 
    "q_en": "What was the name of Princess Diana's boyfriend who was with her when she was killed in a car accident?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "查爾斯王子的情人叫什麼名字？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of Crown Prince Charles' lover?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「在日朝鮮人總聯合會」中，有多少比率的人的故鄉在南韓？", 
    "q_en": "What percent of Chongryun-affiliated Korean residents in Japan have their hometowns in South Korea?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "小出義雄先生所寫的書，書名為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the book by Yoshio Koide titled?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本第一位贏得奧林匹克運動會金牌的女性運動員是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who was Japan's first women's athletics Olympic gold medalist?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_WINNER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本第一次全國國勢調查在何時辦理？", 
    "q_en": "When was the first national census conducted?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "參加雪梨奧運的選手中，女性佔多少比率？", 
    "q_en": "What percent of participants in the Sydney Olympics were female?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "第一個參加奧運的日本女性運動員是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who is the first Japanese woman to take part in the Olympic Games?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_FIRSTPERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1928年奧運在哪裡舉行？", 
    "q_en": "Where was the 1928 Olympic Games held?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本女星都蝶蝶的自傳名稱為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of Chocho Miyako's autobiography?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本女星都蝶蝶的先生叫什麼名字？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of Chocho Miyako's husband?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "在一天當中的什麼時候，「甦醒的三宅島」演奏會將要舉行？", 
    "q_en": "At what time of day will the concert, \"Revive Miyakejima,\" be held?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_TIME"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "哪個交響樂團將在「甦醒的三宅島」演奏會中表演？", 
    "q_en": "Which orchestra will perform in \"Revive Miyakejima\"?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "根據日本運輸省的預估推算，2010年時，死於交通事故的高齡者，將高於1999年人數的百分之多少", 
    "q_en": "According to the calculation by the Transport Ministry, what percent higher will the death toll of elderly people in traffic accidents in 2010 be than that of 1999?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "根據估計推算，1999年至2010年期間，高齡人口將增加多少百分比？", 
    "q_en": "By what percent is the population of elderly people estimated to increase during the 1999-2010 period?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "根據估計推算，1999年至2010年期間，持有駕照的高齡人口將增加多少百分比？", 
    "q_en": "By what percent will the population of the aged with driver's licenses increase during the 1999-2010 period?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「狸」這本書的作者是誰？", 
    "q_en": "Who wrote \"Tanuki\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本女星山田五十鈴在歷經七十年的演藝生涯後，獲得什麼獎章？", 
    "q_en": "What award did Isuzu Yamada receive after seven decades of her career as an actress?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRIZE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本為幫助尚比亞普及蚊帳使用所舉辦的募款活動，共募得多少日圓？", 
    "q_en": "How much money has been donated to a fund-raising campaign to expand the use of mosquito nets in Zambia?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本難民救助會購買一個蚊帳要花多少美元？", 
    "q_en": "What does the Association for Aid and Relief pay for a piece of mosquito net?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本難民救助會希望用多少錢購買一個蚊帳？", 
    "q_en": "How much does the Association for Aid and Relief ask for a piece of mosquito net?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "美國柯林頓總統夫人叫什麼名字？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of the wife of President Clinton?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "報知新聞社頒發給松井秀喜和片岡篤史等人的獎項名稱為何？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of an award given to people such as Hideki Matsui or Atsushi Kataoka by The Hochi Shimbun?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRIZE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日本黃金心靈獎和美國大聯盟的哪個獎項類似？", 
    "q_en": "What is the name of Major League's award similar to Japan's Golden Spirit Award?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRIZE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "高野悅子描述她母親到去世前的人生的書，書名是？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the book by Etsuko Takano describing her mother's life until her death?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "根據門野晴子原著，由槙坪多鶴子所導演的電影是哪一部？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of the film based on a story by Haruko Kadono and directed by Tazuko Makitsubo?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「老親」這部電影是根據哪個作者的作品？", 
    "q_en": "On whose story is \"Roshin\" based?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "在日本有多少比率的失竊車歸還失主？", 
    "q_en": "What percent of stolen cars are returned to their owners?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "在英國，因公務騎乘自行車時，公司每英哩會補助多少金額？", 
    "q_en": "How much is a company employee paid per mile by the company when using a bicycle for business purposes?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "在埃塞俄比亞所發現的古猿人「露西」的身高多高？", 
    "q_en": "How tall was Lucy, the Hominid discovered in Ethiopia?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_HEIGHT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "外國語文翻譯成日文，和日文翻譯成外國語言的書籍相比較，其比率是多少？", 
    "q_en": "What is the ratio of foreign books translated into Japanese to Japanese books translated into foreign languages?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "請舉出在美國、德國或英國等處廣為周知的日本作家。", 
    "q_en": "Name some Japanese writers who are well known in countries like the United States, Germany, or Great Britain.", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_INVENTORS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "世界兒童高峰會在哪一年舉行？", 
    "q_en": "In what year was the World Summit for Children held?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "根據「2001年世界兒童白皮書」的報告，使用在三歲以下幼兒照護費用中的每一美元，相當於節省多少他長大成人後的醫療費用？", 
    "q_en": "According to the State of the World's Children 2001 white paper, for every dollar spent on caring for a child under the age of 3, how much can be saved on health care when the child grows up?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "布希陣營在競選2000年總統時，總共花費多少美元？", 
    "q_en": "How much did the Bush camp spent during the 2000 presidential campaign?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "高爾陣營在競選2000年總統時，總共花費多少美元？", 
    "q_en": "How much did the Gore camp spent during the 2000 presidential election campaign?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "在北韓雲何里建造風車的是哪個單位？", 
    "q_en": "Who built windmills in Unhari, North Korea?", 
    "q_type": "ORGANIZATION",
	"q_sub": "ORGANIZATION_OTHER"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "在北韓雲何里建造的風車，一台要花費多少日圓？", 
    "q_en": "How much does it cost to build a windmill in Unhari?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "大隈講堂的時鐘塔，高度是多少？", 
    "q_en": "What is the height of the clock tower of Okuma Kodo hall?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_HEIGHT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "大隈講堂何時開館啟用？", 
    "q_en": "When was Okuma Kodo hall opened?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_DATE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "日俄戰爭何時發生？", 
    "q_en": "When did the Russo-Japanese War take place?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "松尾芭蕉的作品名稱為何？", 
    "q_en": "What did Basho Matsuo write?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "PRESS"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "喬治魯卡斯第一部廣受好評的作品是哪一部電影？", 
    "q_en": "What is the title of George Lucas' first widely acclaimed movie?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "ARTIFACT_ENTERTAINMENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「新人類」一詞，何時開始成為時髦語彙？", 
    "q_en": "When did the term \"shin jinrui\" come into vogue?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "達克明子住在美國哪裡？", 
    "q_en": "Where does Akiko Docker live?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_PROVINCE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "成人日是根據哪個法律所定？", 
    "q_en": "Under which law was Coming-of-Age Day established?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "LAW"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "KSD公司一年的營收有多少日圓？", 
    "q_en": "What is the annual business income of KSD?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "古關忠男一年的收入有多少日圓？", 
    "q_en": "How much was Tadao Koseki paid annually?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "古關忠男住在哪裡？", 
    "q_en": "Where did Tadao Koseki live?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_BUILDING"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「振袖火事」發生於何時？", 
    "q_en": "When did the furisode (long-sleeved kimono) fire break out?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_DATE"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "回向院位於何處？", 
    "q_en": "Where is Ekoin located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "本妙寺位於何處？", 
    "q_en": "Where is Honmyoji located?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_CITY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "甘乃迪於何時就任美國總統？", 
    "q_en": "When was Kennedy inaugurated as President of the United States?", 
    "q_type": "TIME",
	"q_sub": "TIME_YEAR"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "「不要問國家為你們做些什麼；要問你們能為國家做些什麼？」這句話是誰說的？", 
    "q_en": "Who said, \"Ask not what your country can do for you -- ask what you can do for your country\"?", 
    "q_type": "PERSON",
	"q_sub": "PERSON_PERSON"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "在日美合作民意調查中，多少比率的美國人表示相信他們的總統？", 
    "q_en": "What percent of Americans polled in a joint Japan-U.S. survey said they trusted their president?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_PERCENT"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "內閣官房和外務省年度機密預算總共有多少日圓？", 
    "q_en": "What is the total amount of the annual confidential funds allocated to the Cabinet Secretariat and the Foreign Ministry?", 
    "q_type": "NUMBER",
	"q_sub": "NUMBER_MONEY"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "1977年荷蘭航空和泛美航空於何處相撞意外？", 
    "q_en": "Where did the 1977 collision of a KLM plane and a PanAm plane take place?", 
    "q_type": "LOCATION",
	"q_sub": "LOCATION_ISLAND"
  }, 
  {
    "q_zh": "海上自衛隊所擁有的潛水艇名稱為何？", 
    "q_en": "What are submarines of the Maritime Self-Defense Force called?", 
    "q_type": "ARTIFACT",
	"q_sub": "VEHICLE"
  }, 
  {
